Mattia Amadio

Climate and disaster risk specialist

Climate risk scientist with 10 years of experience in the field of hydrometeorological hazards and disaster risk management. I have been involved in academic research projects over multiple countries, working with many highlyranked international institutions. In 2010 I was awarded a PhD in Science and Management of Climate Change from the Ca' Foscari University of Venice.



Since 2018 I am part of the World Bank's GFDRR, contributing to numerous WB projects. My expertise covers geoanalytics and mapping, impact modelling and climate change. I am a science enthusiast with a pragmatic attitude.

+39 3488441401



Venice, Italy



bit.ly/disasterologist

WORK EXPERIENCE

Short-term consultant

GFDRR, World Bank

2018 – Present

Washington DC (US) - Remote

- Climate hazards and disaster risk analytics over 30 countries (CDDR and other DRR projects)
- Geodata review, management and processing (ThinkHazard!; GFDRR GeoNode; BRI; country profiles)
- Risk Data Library and CCDR tools design and development

Contact: Pierre Chrzanowski

Asian Development Bank

2021 - 2023

Manila (PH) - Remote

o Development of Climate and Disaster Risk screening and assessment tool

Contact: Charles A. Rodgers; Belinda Hewitt

Academic researcher

Euro-Mediterranean Centre on Climate Change

Research foundation on climate change

- Climate-KIC project SAFERPLACES, flash-flood hazard from extreme precipitations and risk mitigation in European cities (2 years)
- H2020 project CLARA, climate forecast enabled knowledge services (3 years)
- National Climate Change Adaptation Plan (PNACC) for Italy
- o Geospatial analytics support activities under several EUfunded DRR projects

Contact: Jaroslav Mysiak

SKILLS

Spatial analytics

Map Design

Python

Geodata management

LANGUAGES

English	Italian	Spanish
Full Professional	Native Proficiency	Elementary Proficiency
Proficiency		

LATEST PUBLICATIONS

12/2021

Journal article

Cost-benefit analysis of coastal flood defence measures in the North Adriatic Sea

M. Amadio, A.H. Essenfelder, S. Bagli, S. Marzi et al.

Natural Hazards and Earth System Sciences

Cost-benefit analysis of coastal flood defence infrastructures in Italy considering the effects of climate change.

2021

Study report

Investment in Disaster Risk Management in Europe makes economic sense

GFDRR, ECA

The World Bank

Reporting for DG-ECHO on Cost-Benefit analysis of existing DRM projects in the EU.

Study report

Disasters, Conflict, and Displacement: Intersectional **Risks in South Sudan**

GFDRR, IOM

The World Bank

Part one: analytic mapping of intersectional risks for South Sudan based on existing data and assessments related to natural hazards and conflict and fragility.

03/2019

Journal article

Testing empirical and synthetic flood damage models: the case of Italy

M. Amadio, A.R. Scorzini, F. Carisi, A.H. Essenfelder et al.

Natural Hazards and Earth System Sciences

Study to evaluate the predictive performance of existing flood damage models in comparison with empirical losses.

EDUCATION

PhD in Science and Management of Climate Change

Ca' Foscari University

09/2015 - 12 / 2018

Venice (IT)

o Thesis title: Integrated Framework for Flood Risk Assessment in Italy. The thesis consists of four research articles published on academic journals.